# 哈喽大家好
Hello everyone
# 最近我伯爷家的这只母鸡跟狗打架
Recently my uncle's hen had a fight with his dog
# 狗把它咬伤了
The dog hurt it bad
# 今早晨放出来狗跟都它按（追）就把它咬伤了
This morning the dog chase it and bit it hard
# 咬伤了喂起还不是要瘦 弄来宰来吃了哎呀
Now that it's hurt. Even if I keep feeding it, it'll become thinner. Let's just butcher and eat it.
# 所以说狗跟鸡打架的话 吃亏的是鸡
So if a dog fights with a chicken, the chicken is always inferior
# 我们不可能把狗给宰了
We can't butcher the dog anyway
# 做啥子
What do we cook?
# 还是拿这个嘛 拿这个干海椒弄来炒辣子鸡
What about this... Cook 'La zi ji' with these dry chili peppers
# 要得啊
OK
# 我们把它做成辣子鸡
Let's cook it into 'La zi ji' (Chicken with chili)
# 我们做辣子鸡的话 这个鸡就稍微砍小一点
Generally in this dish, the chicken should be chopped into small dices
# 这个是狗咬过的
This was bitten by the dog
# 这个脖子
The neck
# 就拿给它吃
Let's give it to the dog then
# 狗儿咯 来
Come on, doggy!
# 这鸡要跟它抢啊
The rooster is competing with it
# 它蹭到吃的就走了
The rooster goes away once it gets some food
# 我们这个辣子鸡要提前放7、8成的盐把它腌一下
In this dish, we need to add 70% to 80% salt in advance to marinate the chicken
# 要让它提前入味
To let the flavor penetrate inside before cooking
# 如果我们鸡肉已经炒好了再放盐就没有意义了
It'll make no sense to add salt after the chicken is fully cooked
# 盐是进不去的那个时候
Salt won't get inside then
# 好了我们这个肉腌好了 给它放十分钟
Ok. The chicken is ready and let's marinate it for 10 minutes
# 现在准备一下配料
Now prepare the side ingredients
# 这个配料特别简单 就只要一坨老姜几颗大蒜
It's very simple. Just a piece of old ginger, some garlic
# 然后再剪一点这个干辣椒 这个灯笼椒
Then scissor some dry chili peppers. The "Denglongjiao" (aka lantern chilis)
# 我们还是用上次的灯笼椒 我伯爷不能吃太辣
We are still using the "Denglongjiao" last time. My uncle can't eat too spicy food
# 然后这个姜的话切成姜末 还有蒜也切成蒜末
Here we mince the ginger and garlic
# 切小一点更入味
Small pieces are better for flavor penetration
# 我们干辣椒用这个剪一碗就行了
One bowl (like this) of dry chili peppers would be enough
# 我们那个鸡也差不多一碗 干辣椒也用一碗
The chicken also fills a bowl. The same amount for chili peppers
# 然后在体积上面的话1:1就可以了
The ratio of chicken to chili is 1:1 in terms of volume
# 1:1多不多了点哦
Is 1:1 too much? #这里不确定是谁比谁多...
# 不多
Nope
# 我们在外面（吃）的话辣子鸡是在辣椒里面找鸡（肉）
When ordering this dish in restaurants, we need to look for chicken in chili pepper
# 外面的话它的辣椒量更多 纯粹就是把干辣椒盖过这个鸡肉
They use much more chili pepper. It's almost like covering the chicken with chili.
# 好 我们这个干辣椒就剪得差不多了
Ok. That's all for the chili.
# 满满的一大碗 等一下再筛一下这个籽
A full bowl of chili pepper. I'll need to remove the seeds later
# 籽要去掉一些 要不然待会儿吃的话满口都是籽 这样就不好了
We should remove some seeds. Otherwise, we'll eat too many seeds, which will spoil this dish
# 给它稍微漏（筛）几哈 这个米米太多了
Let's sieve it. There're too many seeds
# 太多了炒出来糊糊呀呀的
The dish will be spoiled with too many seeds #不是很理解糊糊呀呀是啥哈哈哈
# 这个籽就不要了 倒了
We don't need these seeds. Let's throw them away
# 这哈子又在上面筛
Now sieve the chili peppers up here
# 看 都还多得很
Look. We've still got a lot
# 但是又不能说一点籽都不要
However, we shouldn't throw away all seeds
# 没有籽的话又不香了 只是说不能太多
We'll lose the aroma without seeds. Just not too many
# 这样筛两遍就可以了
Sieve it twice like this
# 好 这个籽也不要了 就行了
Ok. Throw away the seeds here as well and it's done
# 最后我们来加一点花椒
Finally let's add some Sichuan peppercorns
# 辣子鸡花椒也是一大灵魂之一
Sichuan peppercorns are also one of the souls of this dish
# 3、4斤的肉噶
We have... 3 to 4 Jin (~1.5 - 2 kg) of chicken, huh?
# 抓两把
Two handfuls of Sichuan peppercorns
# 好 可以了
Ok. That's enough
# 锅中加入适量的菜籽油
Add a moderate amount of rapeseed oil into the wok
# 加入准备好的花椒和鸡肉
Add the Sichuan peppercorns and the chicken
# 四伯爷 这会等它慢慢炒
Uncle, now let's stir-fry it slowly
# 这个水没炒干的话这个肉就不香
If the moisture is not dried out, the meat won't taste good
# 锅中加入干辣椒
Add the dry chili pepper into the wok
# 把这个干辣椒拿下去跟它一起炒
Now we stir-fry the chicken with the chili pepper
# 四伯爷你来炒哈儿嘛
Uncle, would you have a try?
# 试哈嘛
Just have a try
# 我炒都炒不来
I don't think I can do it
# 不翻 就这样炒哈就是
You don't need to flip the food. Just stir it like this
# 还是你来
You'll do it better
# 我不行
I can't
# 翻不转是不哦
Can't flip the food, right?
# 锅中加入准备好的姜蒜末
Add the minced ginger and garlic into the wok
# （味道）辣不辣
Is it too spicy?
# 锅中加入切好的火锅底料
Add hot pot ingredient (cut into pieces in advance) into the wok
# 撒点芝麻
Sprinkle some sesame
# 然后关火
Turn off the heat
# 最后加点鸡精
Finally, add some chicken bouillon
# 好
Okay
# 把它和转（匀）了之后就可以起锅了
Stir the food uniformly and it's ready to serve!
# 好 出锅
Ok. It's ready!
# 好大一盆哦
That's a large bowl of chicken
# 害怕有几斤哦
Might be several 'Jin' in weight
# 尝哈看 伯爷伯娘
Please take a bite, uncle and aunt
# 好 试哈看嘛
Sure. Let me try it
# 这个肉这样炒起不得老也不得干
The meat is neither too chewy nor too dry
# 而且它还香也咬得动
Tastes good and easy to chew
# 你看这种
Look
# 四伯爷这种小的是肉大的是骨头
Uncle, the small pieces like this are meat. Larger pieces are bones
# 你看肉跟骨头都炒脱骨了
You've seperated the meat from the bones during cooking
# 香不香
Does it taste good?
# 香安 是有点好吃这个东西
Sure. Delicious indeed
# 下酒哦 安逸噶
Best with beer. That'll be nice
# 下啤酒安逸安
Nice with beer
# 今天我们这个辣子鸡没有用宽油来炸
Today we didn't use 'kuan you' to fry the chicken in this dish
# 就是考虑到我伯爷
Because my uncle...
# 如果宽油炸的话这个鸡肉收缩的比较厉害 就咬不动
If the chicken is fried, the meat will shrink hard. He won't be able to chew it
# 我们这个既香又辣 然后肉又不硬特别入味
In this way, it tastes delicious and spicy. The meat is tender with flavors fully penetrated
# 好吃
Yummy!
# 好吃 跟茄猫儿（青蛙）肉样
Yummy. Tastes like frog
# 好了 大家家里有土鸡的可以试一下
Okay. If you have free-range chicken, just have a try
# 没有土鸡的可以到市场去买
Otherwise, you can buy it in the markets
# 买肉鸡
Broiler chicken is also fine
# 哎呀 一般好多农村哪个这样整来干哦
Hmm. Few people in the countryside would do this
# 成本好高哦
It's so expensive
# 嗯
Yep
# 好 本期视频就到这里
Ok. That's the end of this video
# 我去给你开罐啤酒 四伯爷
Let me get you a can of beer, uncle